Why do people think it's bad or
dangerous for kids to lift weights? And
probably the most common one which we
will talk about, why do we think it
stunts growth? I'll give you a spoiler
alert. It doesn't. But where did this
even all to get started? Well, most of
the time there's a direct and simple
reason. And in this case, it's no
different. You have to go all the way
back to the 1960s. Couple things to pay
attention to. Number one, exercise
science was not a field until really the
1960s and didn't really take off until
the 70s and 80s. So upwards at that
time, pediatric medicine also wasn't
really much of a field. And so prior to
the 1960s, we didn't have any
information. And I think it's fair for
parents and other leaders to be cautious
about things when you have no data to go
off of. And so from a starting default
place, I think it was reasonable to say
we don't know if it's safe. Therefore,
we're just going to assume it's not safe
until shown otherwise. And that's an
okay default position. More specifically
here, the very first paper that shot
this thing off was a a really renowned
study in this field that came out of
Japan again in the
1960s. And what it found was an
association between kids who were
involved in high amounts of hard labor
being shorter in life. Now, the ability
to look back at this, you know, some 80
years later, obviously you can in your
head and and all of you astute
scientists now are able to think, okay,
wait a minute, what are probably some of
the confounding factors that are
associated with this? Kids doing a lot
of hard labor, probably other things
going on, malnutrition, environmental
toxins, lots of other issues that are
going to contribute to them not being as
tall as they should have been. But at
that time it was an association and
again no other information. They just
assumed then that even though again the
study was not in strength training to be
really clear. There was just an
association with hard manual labor in
kids was going to stunt your growth. And
that myth persisted for decades mostly
because we just didn't have any other
information.
1970s 1980s there wasn't a lot of
research again coming out on kids. Not a
lot of research at all, if any, on kids
in strength training. By the time the
1990s came around, the National Strength
and Conditioning Association, NSCA, I've
spoken about this organization many,
many times. The research was there. This
organization was all over it advocating
for strength training. The science was
coming out. And so now the general
culture was, you can't really argue it's
bad for kids anymore. But they weren't
really strongly arguing that you have to
go out and do it either. It was kind of
just like a well it's okay it's not as
dangerous as we thought so it's fine but
no one was really banging on the door to
say get kids in the weight room get them
to start lifting outside of the NSCA
group things changed dramatically in
2008 this point there was enough data
and research that it was really really
positive for kids and so people had to
start changing these policy statements
2020 actually a big update came from
this policy stand and now it is just
inarguable that The benefits are not
only small, but they are large. They are
robust, and they cover a lot of
different areas. And it is overall a
fantastic and amazing activity for kids.
If you enjoyed this clip, you can watch
the full episode by clicking here.